Well, it's time to get this show on the road, quite literally.
At this stage, we have this illusion of motion, like how our car's driving along a highway and we
have the ability to control our car by turning it left or right.
But now we need to focus on getting our obstacle cars on the road.
These are the cars that we're going to be weaving in between as we play through our game.
As you can see, at this stage we only have one car sprite, but soon you will see how from it we can
create an endless amount of cars.
And again, before we just start coding, let's think about what it needs to do.
And then we can consider how we will achieve this with code.
So to further the illusion of motion and to add an obstacle that we must avoid, we want this car to
look like it is driving at a slower speed than our car.
So it would be coming slowly down a lane like this, and then we would need to dodge it by turning left
or right.
So let's try to tackle the first problem moving over to our car sprite.
We can first attach a forever block onto this current script, and simply all we will do is have the
car slowly move down the screen by changing the Y by a negative value of, say, five.
Then hitting play.
Well, that looks perfect because it's coming down the road.
It still looks like it's moving forward because it's moving back slower than the road is moving back.
But now that we have this call moving, you can see it just stops when it gets to the end of the screen.
And this works perfectly well.
Perfect if all we want is one obstacle in our game, which isn't the goal here.
So instead we need the car to go back to the start of our screen when it reaches the bottom.
And well, to do this we need to add some sort of condition check.
But if you move over to our motion group, if you remember, we have this Y position and we can use
this to check what the y position is of our sprite, which means we can check to see if our sprite has
reached the end of the screen, and if it has, we can make it go back to the top.
So firstly, what we need is an if statement.
And you will notice here that you can't put this y position block in the if statement.
And well for obvious reasons it's like if y position then do something.
Well that doesn't make sense.
What we need to do is check the y position is lower than a certain value.
And just like with our road lines, we can do this by grabbing this green block from the operators group.
This is what checks if a value is greater than or less than another.
Remember to pay attention to the size at the start.
Here it's going from a size that is less than where it starts, and here it's going from a size that
is greater than.
So we want to check if y is less than -210, which is basically the bottom of the screen.
Now, if this condition is true, we want our car to go back to the top of the screen.
So all we need to do is bring in a go to block and set the Y value to 210, which is basically the top
of the screen, and hit play.
What?
As you can see, our car drives down and when it reaches the bottom, it goes back to the top.
It's nice.
So that's looking pretty good.
But there's still one more thing we need to address.
And that's our car.
Well, it keeps coming down the same lane, which would make the game pretty easy, because all you
would need to do is drive in any of the other lanes and we would win.
And we don't want cheap wins here.
So what we need is for the car to somehow randomly switch between each of these lanes every time it
goes back to the top.
Now, this is a little bit more tricky than you might think, but let's start with what we know.
So we know that this will have something to do with the x value, as right now we set it to zero each
time it goes to the top.
So we need to change that.
We also know that as something to do with picking a random number.
So to start off with, let's just bring the pick random into the go to x.
Now we can see what the upper and lower limits will be by dragging our car to the first lane.
Yeah, you can see it is at -145.
And the last line is well.
145.
So we can have X be set to a random number from -145 to 145.
And if we hit play, you can see that each time our car reaches the end.
It switches lanes, which is good, but the problem is that sometimes it goes in between our lanes,
which isn't good.
And this is where it gets a little tricky.
So we need to change the way we approach this.
So instead of setting the number between -145 and 145, we need to do a bit of math.
Yeah.
Fun, right?
Huh.
So what we need is a plus block and a times block, and you'll see why.
So our X position of our car can be a minimum of -145.
So we can enter that into our first plus input.
Now there are five.
Different possible lanes that our car can be in at any moment.
So what we need to do is work out the space between the lanes.
So our first lane is -145.
If we move it to the second lane it's at -70.
Now one 4570.
It gives you 75.
But we can just say around 75.
So 75 is the distance between the lanes.
So if we move this times block into the plus block we can enter 75.
And as there are five lanes we can again use pick randomly.
And here we can set it to zero and four.
And yeah zero seems weird.
Why not 1 to 5.
And this is because well -145 is our first lane and anything times zero.
So if the random number is zero our car will be in our first lane.
And I know this might be a bit confusing, but as you work more with these types of blocks, the better
you understand it.
But enough said.
Let's see this in action.
Well, that looks almost perfect, but we can adjust it just a smidge to get even better.
As you can see, the last line is a bit far.
So let's just change this to be 74 because it's all about trial and error.
But yeah, that looks really good.
So now just sit back, relax and enjoy your creation because it's only going to get better.